Guide to the Iser Steiman Papers
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
Iser Steiman papers
1943-1975
1943-1960
Ms Coll 27
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
0.21
(1 box)
The papers consist primarily of letters between Iser Steiman and John F. Fulton from 1943 to Fulton's death in 1960. Both sides of the correspondence are available as Steiman kept copies of his own letters. Other correspondents include Madeline Stanton, Harriet Thomson, and Wiliam C. Gibson. Topics include avaiation medicine; Steiman's translations of Soviet Russian works on military medicine; and history of medicine. Also part of the collection is a copy of a typewritten autobiography by Steinman which traces his career up to his arrival at Yale in 1944.
Steiman, Iser, 1898-1981
Fulton, John F. (John Farquhar), 1899-1960
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Marcie Steiman Smordin, daugher of Iser Steiman, 2009.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Iser Steiman emigrated from Latvia to Canada at the age of 14 and received his M.D. from the University of Manitoba in 1924. He became a pioneer rural family doctor in Kamsack, Saskatchewan, where he built his own hospital, the King Edward Hospital. In World War II, he joined the Royal Canadian Airforce. Because of his growing interest in aviation medicine and his discovery of a recent textbook in Russian, his superiors requested him to translate it. In the process of preparing the translation, he was introduced to John F. Fulton, Sterling professor of physiology at Yale School of Medicine. Steiman's translation, The Fundamentals of Aviation Medicine, was published in Torono in 1943. In 1944, on Fulton's initiative, Steiman was posted to work with the aeromedical research unit at Yale. After the war, Steiman moved to Vancouver where he practiced medicine, translated other medical works from Russian, and wrote on the history of medicine.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist primarily of letters between Iser Steiman and John F. Fulton from 1943 to Fulton's death in 1960. Both sides of the correspondence are available as Steiman kept copies of his own letters. Other correspondents include Madeline Stanton, Harriet Thomson, and Wiliam C. Gibson. Topics include avaiation medicine; Steiman's translations of Soviet Russian works on military medicine; and history of medicine. Also part of the collection is a copy of a typewritten autobiography by Steinman which traces his career up to his arrival at Yale in 1944.
Arrangement
One series. Correspondence arranged chronologically, followed by the autobiography.
Aviation medicine -- Soviet Union; Aviation medicine -- United States; Medicine -- History; Physicians -- Canada; Translating and interpreting; Gibson, William C. (William Carleton), 1913-2009; Stanton, Madeline E. (Madeline Earle); Steiman, Iser, 1898-1981; Thomson, Elizabeth Harriet, 1907-; King Edward Hospital -- Kamsack (Sask.)
- Correspondence, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Correspondence, 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Correspondence, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Correspondence, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Correspondence, 1969, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Autobiography (62 pages, photocopy), after 1956 (Box 1, Folder 16)